In the Middle Ages, the most important
worship place in the City of London
was Saint Paul’s Cathedral, a magnificent
Gothic structure whose mass dominated the
skyline of the medieval city even from
the opposite side of the Thames river.
Saint Paul’s enormous nave, was longer
than that of any other cathedral in Europe,
and its legendary spire, taller
even than the Great Pyramid of Giza,
made the cathedral the second tallest
structure in the world at the time.
Saint Paul’s Cathedral rose upon Ludgate Hill, the
highest point of Londinium, the old Roman city.
Construction began in 1087 over the
ruins of an earlier small church.
Saint Paul’s started as a Norman Romanesque
structure, with rounded arches and small windows,
but due to fires and problems within the
kingdom, the construction was long delayed.
At the time, architecture was ever on the change,
and the builders didn’t trouble themselves to
follow the style in which a building had been
begun, but went on with whatever was in use then.
By the 12th century, Gothic architecture had
become the standard for church building across
Europe, and because churches often took
centuries to complete, most cathedrals in
England have some Romanesque elements as well as
some early Gothic and some late Gothic elements.
Old Saint Paul’s Cathedral was no
exception: it took so long to build
that it was a very hybrid combination of
Norman Romanesque and Gothic architecture.
The western half was built first, so
it retained its Romanesque appearance:
smaller windows, round arches, and a thicker,
more massive wall with a lesser need for flying
buttresses, which were evidently added later.
And the eastern half was built later, thus you
can notice it looks more Gothic in its forms,
with pointed arches in the windows and vaults.
Also the Cathedral was heavily repaired and
modified over the centuries, so the most
striking elements such as the exquisite rose
window at the east were in the Gothic style.
The spire was a structure of timber covered with
lead, and it reached a height of 149 meters,
making Old Saint Paul’s the second
tallest building on Earth at the time,
just behind Lincoln’s Cathedral, in central
England, whose spire reached 160 meters.
In 1561, during a severe thunderstorm,
Saint Paul’s spire was struck by lightning,
and caught fire, making the entire spire
collapse, and it was never rebuilt.
The front facade had a distinctly
Romanesque character, featuring
solid masonry walls with small windows, and
deep, round archivolts framing the doors.
The Great Cathedral of Saint Paul, glorious
as it was, the finest in England in its time,
lasted on for nearly six centuries, but
after the Reformation, it began to decline.
The English Reformation led to the destruction of
interior ornamentation such as altars, shrines,
chapels, and crypts, as well as several
religious buildings in the churchyard,
which were seized by the crown and sold
as shops to protestant booksellers.
By the end of the sixteenth century,
the cathedral had lost its spire,
its walls were falling into disrepair,
and much of its heritage had been lost.
The great nave, once a place of worship, became
known as Paul’s Walk, and had become a market,
and the place in London where you’d go to hear
the latest news and to do business, but also a
place to pick up gossip and even prostitutes,
a place infested by beggars and thieves.
In 1621, King James appointed Inigo Jones,
the first Renaissance architect in England,
to repair the structure of the
Cathedral, and to rebuild some parts.
In the 1630s Jones added a
Classical porch to the front.
In the early 1660s Christopher Wren,
a mathematician and astronomer,
with some experience as an
architect, was appointed to
restore the building matching the style
of Inigo Jones’s additions in the 1630s,
and he proposed to demolish part of the central
tower, and replace it with a Renaissance dome.
Even though his design was approved
and restoration works started,
Saint Paul’s Cathedral was destroyed
in the Great Fire of London in 1666.
The vaults of most Gothic cathedrals are usually
made of stone, but the vaults of the old Saint
Paul’s Cathedral were made of wood, and
therefore much more vulnerable to fire,
which affected the ultimate fate of the
building, reducing the structure to ruins.
Christopher Wren was appointed to oversee
the rebuilding of London after the fire,
thanks to the ingenious plan that he
proposed for the reconstruction of
the city, and he designed over fifty
parish churches to be reconstructed,
all with a unique design that explored
new ideas of light, space, and order.
Yet his greatest achievement,
his architectural masterpiece would
be the new Saint Paul’s Cathedral.
The destruction of the old cathedral was
not total, and at first Wren began a partial
rebuilding of it, but by 1668, it became clear
that a complete reconstruction was necessary,
so he proposed his first
design for the new cathedral:
A centralized plan in the shape of a Greek
cross, whose arms were connected by a
series of curved quadrants instead of the
traditional solution of right angles found
in Bramante’s or Michelangelo’s original
plans for Saint Peter’s Basilica in Rome.
Wren incorporated a round choir on the east side,
and a large domed crossing similar
to that of Saint Peter’s Basilica.
When making his famous
wooden model for the church,
Wren added a projecting western vestibule
to his design, capped by a smaller dome.
As you can see from Wren’s model and later
drawings, this design takes much from
Michelangelo’s architecture: his colossal order on
the exterior pilasters, his Pantheon-like portico,
and the huge dome as an urban element that’s
meant to be seen from anywhere in the city.
However, this design was ultimately
dismissed by the clergy because it
seemed too different from the rest of
English cathedrals and too similar to
the Roman Catholic Churches that were being
built in Rome at the time, such as Saint Peter.
The clergy desired a more traditional basilical
plan with a long nave, transepts and choir,
more similar to the plan of the old
cathedral that had burned in 1666.
Although now protestants, they were very used
to the architectural program of the medieval
Catholic type of plan, as they had been in
use for centuries in England, and they had a
certain rejection for the baroque character that
the Catholics were defining in the continent.
So Christopher Wren redesigned the entire
project, returning to a Latin cross plan.
He added a great octagonal space in the
crossing and a dome topped by a spire.
It’s kind of trying to hold these Italian and
French baroque impulses expressed so strongly
in his previous design, and to make something
that uses a classical language with columns
and round arches, but still reprises the Gothic
image of Old Saint Paul’s Cathedral in its form.
This was the design that was approved,
and its construction began in 1675,
however, Wren as the architect-in-chief of the
construction, was given complete liberty to make
any changes and variations to his own design as
he should see proper during the construction.
So when we see the finished cathedral,
we find a completely different building
to the one that was originally approved.
The final result is a refined building, with
perfect proportions, where you can see a clear
influence of the Renaissance masters
of Italy and France in every element.
Christopher Wren, the architect, was born
at a time when baroque architecture was at
its highest point of development in cities
like Rome or like Paris, and you can really
tell that he visited those cities, and he had
seen the architecture of masters like Bernini,
like Maderno, especially when you
look at details on the facade and
on the elevations of this cathedral as well
as the design of the dome and the towers.
Here are a few examples of direct influence
that Wren drew from other buildings:
The porticoes on the north and
south sides are enlarged copies of
the facade of Santa Maria della Pace
in Rome made by Pietro da Cortona.
The double colonnade on the front portico,
as well as the double pilasters on the sides
are taken from the facade of the
Louvre in Paris by Claude Perrault.
Those lateral windows of the front facade,
recessed in a concave perspective to show the
thickness of the wall for visual strength, are
identical to the top windows found in the Palazzo
Barberini in Rome, made by Francesco Borromini.
And the towers, are also reminiscent
of the architecture of Borromini,
when you compare them to the towers of the
church of Sant’Agnese in Piazza Navona, in Rome:
you can see that classic Borromini curve with the
columns rotated 45 degrees, and they both
have a clock, and a bell shape at the top.
All these elements make the new Saint Paul’s
Cathedral look like a building from
the Renaissance and Baroque period,
however if you focus more on the plan of the
building, on the structure, and on its massing,
you can see the clear influence from
Gothic medieval cathedrals from England.
Saint Paul’s has an extremely
long nave compared to its width,
something typical of the English Gothic,
and the huge crossing space with a dome
replaces the massive central tower
in English Gothic cathedrals.
Wren is trying to make a refined
and academic building with a
classical character that follows the
principles of Renaissance architecture,
but he as a mathematician finds many
solutions that can’t coexist with the
rules of Classical architecture, so he has
to disguise some of the structural elements.
You can see that above the aisle roofs
there are these flying buttresses which
are Gothic elements, present
in most Gothic cathedrals,
so he hides these Gothic elements by raising
the aisle walls creating these screens that
cover them, and thus giving the exterior a good
proportional height in relation to the dome.
These screen walls also act
as counterweight to the flying
buttresses to redirect to the ground
the thrust received by the nave vault,
the same function that the pinnacles
have in Gothic architecture.
To support the dome, Wren combines
different structural principles:
Instead of just supporting a huge dome
over four massive piers like in Saint
Peter’s and other Italian churches, he uses a
Gothic example as inspiration, Ely Cathedral.
Among the medieval cathedrals in England, Ely
Cathedral is very special, because it has a
unique octagonal crossing with a great wooden
vault reaching to a central octagonal lantern,
and what could look like four great piers
in plan, such as those from Saint Peter’s,
seems like they are dematerialized
into eight much lighter piers.
So Wren takes this example and applies
it to the dome of Saint Paul’s.
You have a huge crossing space
with eight thin and delicate piers,
each reaching a small triangular pendentive
that holds the drum of the great dome.
And because these piers are so thin, you don’t
really read them as piers but as columns,
and the structure seems very dematerialized,
and delicate, you get this sense of lightness,
it’s like Wren is interested
in the absence of material.
For the actual dome, Wren followed at a certain
extent the principles of Michelangelo’s cupola
in Rome, but he especially studied
the dome of Les Invalides in Paris,
which employs a triple-dome system:
the innermost dome, made of masonry,
has a great opening at the top through which
your view vanishes to the top of the middle dome,
decorated with a fresco, giving
you a three-dimensional effect.
This middle dome supports the wooden
structure of a third, outer dome.
This strategy creates two scales: an
interior scale that keeps the right
human proportions inside the building,
and an exterior scale that turns the
massive-looking dome into an urban
element visible from the distance.
Since Christopher Wren needed to create a
dome tall enough to dominate London’s skyline,
yet still maintain proper proportion
within the interior of the building,
he adopted the triple-dome
strategy of Les Invalides.
The inner dome is built of masonry
with a small opening at the top that
allows your view to vanish right
to the top of the middle dome.
The middle dome is more of a
brick cone that supports both,
the stone lantern and the wooden
structure of the outer dome.
If you climb up inside, you can walk through the
space between the brick cone, and the outer dome,
where the timber framing and beams that support
the exterior shell rest on the brick structure,
along with thirty-two radiating counter-forts.
If you look at the section of the building,
you can notice that the drum of the cupola
is not vertical, it tapers slightly toward the
top, and the brick cone is not exactly a cone,
but along with the tapering drum, forms a softly
curved profile that isn’t exactly spherical.
The hidden flying buttresses
also have this soft curve.
Christopher Wren was a mathematician, and
along with his colleague Robert Hooke,
another illustrious mathematician of the
time, developed the catenary principle.
The word “catenary” comes from the
Latin “catena” which means chain,
and the principle consists in the idea that the
shape a chain naturally takes when hanging under
its own weight—the catenary curve—is also the most
stable form for an arch or dome when inverted.
In other words, the curve that hangs in tension
becomes the perfect curve to stand in compression.
And this is the structural principle that Wren
used for the middle dome
and the flying buttresses.
He kind of anticipated Antoni Gaudí by a couple
hundred years, but Wren hid these details behind
the classical language of architecture, while
Gaudí created a language from these structural
principles by expressing the true structure
instead of concealing it behind perfect geometry.
The form of the outer dome was inspired
by the architecture of Donato Bramante,
one of the most respected Italian
architects from the High Renaissance.
Wren especially took inspiration from
Bramante’s Tempietto, considered a perfect
gem of the Renaissance because of its proportions
replicating those of ancient Roman round temples.
The colonnade on the drum is formed
of three-quarter columns attached
to radiating buttress walls, having every
fourth intercolumniation filled in solid,
giving an appearance of strength and solidity.
Behind the balustrade above the columns there
is a gallery from where the dome is resting.
At the summit of the dome, there are
eight openings to light the inner domes.
The total height of the dome is 365 feet, a number
that was symbolic for Wren as an astronomer.
At the meeting of the nave and
transepts there are projecting masses,
which express the support of the
dome from the ground upwards.
This dome is certainly one of
the finest domes in Europe.
To reach the top, you must first ascend the round
staircase located in the south side of the nave,
eventually emerging onto the gallery
that encircles the base of the drum.
From here you can appreciate the
spectacular expanse of the nave
and crossing, and especially
the geometric pattern of the
pavement revealed with a clarity that’s
impossible to perceive from ground level.
From there, the ascent continues
within the space between the brick
cone and the outer dome where the
internal structure is fully exposed.
The stairs grow narrower as
you approach the lantern.
Once you reach the lantern there are just
a few stairs left to reach the summit,
and there is a small window there that allows
you to look straight down into the crossing.
From the top of the dome, you can see the entire
city of London, the Thames with its bridges,
the modern skyline beyond, and
in the distance, Westminster.
This view must have been overwhelming
at the time the cathedral was completed,
thanks to the skyline filled
with spires and monuments.
It remained so until the late twentieth century,
for no building in the city rose higher than
Saint Paul’s Cathedral, but London’s harmonious
skyline was eventually lost to modern skyscrapers.
The interior of Saint Paul’s is comprised
by a long nave reminiscent of medieval
cathedrals in its volume, but expressed in
a classical language through its decoration.
The piers are ornamented with Corinthian
pilasters supporting an entablature and attic,
above which are formed flat saucer
domes inspired by those in the church
of Val-de-Grâce in Paris, which Wren had visited.
Upon entering, you’ll notice
that most of the light inside
the cathedral is admitted through the
clerestory at the top of the nave.
These clerestory windows are invisible from
outside of the building because
they’re hidden by the screen wall.
The vaults aren’t particularly tall
compared to other European cathedrals.
Lower vaults is something inherited
from English Gothic architecture,
and this makes the dome appear immense,
as it feels much closer to you than other
great domes in Europe such as that
of Saint Peter’s at the Vatican.
Behind the altar there is a three-bay choir
with spectacular wood carving by the sculptor
Grinling Gibbons, who was also responsible
for all the stone sculpture in the cathedral.
Before entering the choir
you encounter exceptional
wrought-iron screens crafted by
the French blacksmith Jean Tijou.
And even here, inside the building you see all
these elements borrowed from Bernini and from
other baroque masters from Italy such as these
hexagonal patterns on the window coffering,
or these Palladian arches in the
vestibule leading to lateral chapels.
In the crypt lies the tomb of Christopher Wren,
with a Latin inscription above that reads:
“subtus conditur huius ecclesiae et urbis
conditor Christophorus Wren, qui vixit annos
ultra nonaginta, non sibi sed bono publico.
Lector, si monumentum requiris, circumspice.”
Below is buried the founder of this
church and city, Christopher Wren,
who lived over ninety years, not for
himself, but for the public good.
Reader, if you seek a
monument of him, look around.
Christopher Wren lived to see the cathedral
completed in 1710, something extremely rare
in terms of great European churches, which
often took several generations to be built.
Wren was one of the few architects to oversee the
entire construction process
and see his work completed.
That’s why when you see Saint Paul’s Cathedral,
it seems to harmonize in a special way:
unlike Saint Peter in Rome which
was built by several architects,
Saint Paul’s dome seems to be
much more a part of the building.
Its grouping with the two fine symmetrical towers,
gives the parts and the whole
a very cohesive harmony.
You can really see how Wren is a great
a synthesizer of the past — absorbing
English Gothic mass and lightness,
French engineering and elegance,
and Italian classicism and baroque
into something uniquely English.
The finished building ranks amongst the finest
Renaissance cathedrals in Europe, and its dome
design defined a model that would be later adopted
by the French in their Pantheon, which was then
copied by the Russians in Saint Isaac’s Cathedral,
and then by the Americans in their state Capitols.
Yet even with such a legacy, none of
them quite match the serene balance
and luminous grandeur of Saint Paul’s itself.
I've made an extended version of this
video where I go into more detail
on the old Saint Paul's Cathedral
as well as a new one, and explore
other places from where Christopher
Wren took inspiration for his work.
This longer video is available
if you join as a channel member.
Thank you so much for watching.
I hope you learned and enjoyed.
Please like this video, subscribe to my channel,
and I'll see you very soon in another episode.
Goodbye!